John Kretzschmar Papers
John Kretzschmar Papers
2006-2018
Kretzschmar, John.
0.5 linear ft.
Clippings, correspondence, printed material relating to American engineer and to plastics generally.
5203337
Biographical History
John Kretzschmar (1933-2018) was an American engineer in the field of plastics. A graduate of the University of Missouri, he founded Blako Industries, a plastics extrusion firm, and was a long-time member of the Society of Plastics Engineers, the Society of the Plastics Industry, Inc., and the Plastics Pioneers Association.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John Kretzschmar Papers contains correspondence-subject files, memorabilia, and printed material.
Correspondence-subject files includes correspondence with colleagues and organizations in the plastics field, as well as notes and outlines for a speech by JK (under "Polyethylene 75th Anniversary").
Memorabilia contains clippings about Kretzschmar and several obituaries and remembrances from his funeral.
Printed material contains issues of a number of newsletters and magazines from plastics-related organizations, as well as some miscellaneous items such as a laminated card "Engaging Our Customers: A New Dialogue About Plastics."
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetically by type or topic.
Related Material
has numerous collections and printed material related to the history and development of the plastics industry. Please to locate related manuscript collections, and refer to to locate printed material.
Separated Material
Two books, Polymer Pioneers by Peter J.T. Morris (1989) and The Story of Erinoid by John Morgan (2008), were transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Six issues of Plastics News (Crain Communications Inc.) were transferred to the general collections for cataloging.
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Plastics; Beall, Glenn.; Judkins, Phillip.; Kretzschmar, John.; Russell, John George, 1940-; Chemical Heritage Foundation.; Plastics Hall of Fame.; Plastics Historical Society.; Engineers -- United States.; Plastics -- Societies, etc.; Plastics industry and trade -- Great Britain.; Plastics industry and trade -- United States.; Polyethylene -- History.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Journals (periodicals); Newsletters.; Research notes.; Engineers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Leigh Kretzschmar, 2019.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Bakelite 100 Years, 2007-2008 (Box 1)
  - Beall, Glenn, 2008-2009 (Box 1)
  - Chemical Heritage Foundation, 2008 (Box 1)
  - Cruse, Jen, 2009 (Box 1)
  - Goodey, Chris and Roy, 2008 (Box 1)
  - LDPE [Low Density Polyethylene] and radar, 2008-2009; includes paper by Phil Judkins (Box 1)
  - Plastics Hall of Fame, 2008; 2012 (Box 1)
  - Plastics Historical Society U.K., 2008-2010 (Box 1)
  - Plastics and Rubber Weekly, 2007; includes correspondence with Glenn Beall (Box 1)
  - Plexiglas, 2008; undated; clippings and other material on the history of Plexiglas (Box 1)
  - Polyethylene 75th Anniversary
    - Conference material, Oct 2008 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and notes, 2008 (Box 1)
    - Kretzschmar's talk, 2008; notes and outline (Box 1)
  - Polymer Pioneers notes, 2010; notes on various individuals mentioned in the book, with page numbers (Box 1)
    A copy of this book is available in the circulating collection. Please to locate.
  - Russell, John George, 2008-2009 (Box 1)
  - Swallow bust, 2009; discussion of bust of chemist and engineer John Swallow, by Fiore de Henriquez, found during excavation on a building site (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Clippings about JK, 2009 (Box 1)
  - Obituaries and remembrances, 2018 (Box 1)
- Printed material
  - BPF [British Plastics Federation] Plastics Timeline, 2008 (Box 1)
  - Chemical Heritage, 2008-2009; journal of the Chemical Heritage Foundation; 2 items (Box 1)
  - PHS Newsletter, 2009-2011; publication of the Plastics Historical Society U.K.; 3 items (Box 1)
  - Plastiquarian, 2006-2012; journal of the Plastics Historical Society U.K.; 8 items (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 2008; undated; clippings, handouts, etc. from various plastics-related organizations (Box 1)